Okay בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today is
the last day of נדה Niddah and of learning of the twelfth
cycle of the... the תלמוד. Talmud. I think they say it's all
over but the shouting, but they did the shouting last time, so
hopefully we'll do some more shouting ourselves. Okay, so we pick up
on the top of ע"ב עמוד ב Ayin Bet Amud Bet and
we are the middle of ע"ב. Ayin Bet. I'm sorry, the middle
of ע"ב עמוד ב, Ayin Bet Amud Bet, and we pick up
where it says... wait
a minute... okay, תנן. Tnan. It's the line that starts with word
מטמא. Mitameh. It's about 14 lines down, it's about three lines over
where there's a little א Aleph in brackets at the beginning of
a line. Okay, so תנן, Tnan, we taught in a משנה, Mishna,
we taught in a משנה, Mishna, הבא
לו יום שלאחריו ושימשה. Hav lo yom she-acharav ve-shimsha.
Okay, our משנה Mishna says that if he went to... if he
went to the מקוה Mikvah the day after a woman saw in
the middle of the 11 days and therefore she has to wait
a little bit of the next day before going into the מקוה.
Mikvah. She's a שומרת יום, Shomeret yom, a woman who observes the
following day, so she saw less than day five of the 11
days, she waits a little day six, she goes to the מקוה
Mikvah ושימשה Ve-shimsha and then she has sex. Now what's going to
happen? Right now it's okay, but if she bleeds later today, retroactively
it will have undermined her מקוה Mikvah and she will have been
a זבה, Zavah, a זבה קטנה Zavah ktanah while going to the
מקוה. Mikvah. So what's the... so what do we say about that
scenario? So the משנה Mishna says הרי זו תרבות רעה. Harei zu
tarbut ra'ah. This is like a bad behavior, you're... you know, this
is a bad upbringing, bad behavior, תרבות רעה, Tarbut ra'ah, מגעו ובעילתו
תלויין, Magau ve-bilat hen tlin,
and everything you touch and if you have sex, it's all in
abeyance, it's all in limbo based on what's going to happen for
the rest of the day. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו
דברי הכל היא? Mai lav divrei hakol hi? Doesn't that seem like
everybody agrees? Because we're still asking maybe בית שמאי Beit Shammai would
rabbinically say you're טמא Tamei the rest of the day even if
you didn't see and that it's not in abeyance? Doesn't that seem
that this is universal, בית שמאי Beit Shammai agrees to this? לאו
בית הלל היא, Lav Beit Hillel hi, it's only בית הלל. Beit
Hillel. דתניא, Detanya, now we have a... we taught in a ברייתא.
Baraita. אמר להן רבי יהודה. Amar len Rabbi Yehuda. Now this Yehuda
doesn't make sense, the side says that the גרסא Girsa should be
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. אמר להן בית שמאי לבית הלל, Amar len
Beit Shammai le-Beit Hillel, so בית שמאי Beit Shammai said to בית
הלל, Beit Hillel, וכי לזו אתם קוראים תרבות רעה? Ve-chi le-zo atem
korin tarbut ra'ah?
This behavior, having sex after touching, after going to the מקוה Mikvah
the next morning, you're... all you're saying is that it's like bad
behavior?
It's you know,
it's very risky here. והלא לא נתכוון זה אלא לבעילת נדה. Velo
lo nitkaven zeh ela le-vilat niddah.
Notice by the way how it shifts to the man, right? You
pointed that out right, that the משנה Mishna starts talking about the
woman, obviously it takes two, but here it's shifting to the man
and this man who's having sex with his wife the morning after
she went to the מקוה, Mikvah, he's just trying to have sex
with a נדה. Niddah. So he's intending, right, he's intending to have
sex with a נדה. Niddah. So the גמרא Gemara says נדה סלקא
דעתך? Niddah salka da'atakh? The first thing the גמרא Gemara gets upset
with is wait a minute, she's not a נדה. Niddah. It's during
the 11 days so it's a זבה, Zavah, it's not a נדה.
Niddah. It's the same prohibition, but it's not a נדה. Niddah. So
the גמרא Gemara says okay אלא אימא לבעילת זבה, Ela eima le-vilat
zavah, fine we mean זבה, Zavah, not נדה. Niddah. It's interesting here
that already in this early text, בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, there's a beginning of maybe conflating of the two categories,
which as we know certainly happened later. Anyway fine, but this guy's
intending to have sex with a זבה. Zavah. So the גמרא Gemara
says... so the גמרא Gemara says אלא אימא לזבה. Ela eima le-zavah.
So the גמרא Gemara says זבה סלקא דעתך? Zavah salka da'atakh? But
she's not even yet a full זבה, Zavah, it's only one day,
it's not three days that she bled. אלא אימא לבעילת שומרת יום
כנגד יום, Ela eima le-vilat shomeret yom keneged yom, rather you should
say that he's trying to have sex with this woman who's a
זבה קטנה, Zavah ktanah, a woman who's watching one day after the
next. Now obviously it doesn't mean, you know, it seems to be
בית שמאי Beit Shammai is saying like he's really trying to transgress,
but he's more saying it's virtual that, I mean, what type of
a responsible person you know goes ahead and does an act which
could easily retroactively turn out to be a prohibited act? So it's
not enough to call it תרבות רעה. Tarbut ra'ah. It is real
transgressing behavior in בית שמאי's Beit Shammai eyes, which the גמרא Gemara
seems to say might be an indication to the position we said
before, that according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai he would actually say
the rest of the day you're considered טמאה Tmeiah rabbinically regardless of
whether or not you see at the end of the day. So
it's not conclusive there, but it might be indicative. So we will
end up... that ends our discussion of what status, rabbinic status בית
שמאי Beit Shammai gives for the remainder of the day. Now we
move on, אתמר, Itmar, it was taught. So still dealing with this
whole question of 11 and 10 and so on, but moving away
from this question of בית שמאי Beit Shammai status for the remainder
of the day.
Can I ask a question? Yes. So you're saying that... we're saying
וכי לזו אתם קוראים תרבות רעה? Ve-chi le-zo atem korin tarbut ra'ah?
You... there are a couple of ways of taking it. I mean,
at face value I would have thought it means like, oh, it's
not such a big deal, right? And then so we're saying, so
given the answer, you're saying that בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says how dare you just call it תרבות רעה? Tarbut
ra'ah? It's as if this guy's trying to sin. So you should
call it much worse. Okay, but to call it much worse or
prohibit it? Yes, we could prohibit the act of sex during... after
she's gone to the מקוה Mikvah for the rest of the day.
But would they go further? Would they say that he's considered טמא
Tamei for the rest of the day or
not
even retroactively? Because he is so offended by just saying like it's
bad, he wants it to be really prohibited. Okay, so that is
a possible indication that בית שמאי Beit Shammai would say she's טמא
tamei even if she did not see. Okay, now we move up.
איתמר, Itmar, we talked about the status of the eleven day, eleventh
day. This is the eleventh day after which this woman cannot be
a זבה, zavah, she can only be a נדה. niddah. So do
you have to wait a little bit of the twelfth day, which
is now the נדה niddah period, is that meaningful at all for
a woman bleeding on day
eleven? Now, what about day ten? So let's take a look. איתמר,
Itmar, עשירי, asiri, how about day ten? Now why is day ten
so different? On the one hand, day ten you can observe day
eleven as a clean day of non-bleeding day and it's still in
the זבה zavah period. So it's meaningful as an act of sort
of of the זבה zavah process. On the other hand, if a
woman bleeds on day ten there is no way it can build
up to a
זבה גדולה. zavah gedolah. If a woman bleeds three consecutive days to
be a זבה גדולה zavah gedolah to need seven clean days, so
if she bleeds ten, eleven and twelve, well ten and eleven make
her זבה קטנה zavah ketannah and twelve makes her a נדה. niddah.
So there's no way that this woman the bleeding on day ten
could make her זבה גדולה. zavah gedolah. And maybe because of that
there is no purpose biblically at least to observe another clean day.
Maybe the whole purpose of observing a clean day was when you
knew you were in the possible process of becoming a זבה גדולה.
zavah gedolah. So that's the question of day
ten. רבי יוחנן אמר עשירי כתשיעי. Rabbi Yochanan amar asiri ketishi. It's
just like day nine. מה תשיעי בעי שימור, mah tishi ba'i shimmur,
the same way day nine biblically requires observing the following day, having
some of the following day בטהרה, betaharah, you know, not bleeding and
then going to the מקווה, mikveh, אף עשירי בעי שימור. af asiri
ba'i shimmur. The same is true about day ten because it's followed
by a day that's still in the זבה zavah period.
ריש לקיש אמר עשירי כאחד עשר. Resh Lakish amar asiri ke'achad asar.
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says ten is like eleven. It does not
have significance, you know, this type of significance of the middle day.
מה אחד עשר לא בעי שימור, mah achad asar lo ba'i shimmur,
the same way day eleven you don't have to biblically observe the
following day because it in no way can make her into a
you know that's already in the נדה niddah period, אף עשירי נמי
לא בעי שימור. af asiri nami lo ba'i shimmur. Even the tenth
day you don't have to biblically observe the following day although it's
in the זבה zavah period, it cannot so build up to make
her זבה גדולה zavah gedolah because you have ten, eleven and then
you're outside of that period. So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says ten
is also different. I gotta tell you even though you know we
פוסקן pasken like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and so on, here ריש
לקיש's Resh Lakish position is to me is a little attractive because
there's a logic that the זבה קטנה zavah ketannah is building up
to being a זבה גדולה zavah gedolah and there can be some
difference when it's day ten and it can't build up to that.
Anyway that's what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says. So the גמרא Gemara
says איכא דמתני לה אהא. ika de-matni la aha. So some say
they're discussing it on our משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה Mishnah discussed day
eleven and they discussed what's the story with day ten. And some
say they're discussing it on the following statement. אמר לו רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה לרבי עקיבא. Amar lo Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah le-Rabbi Akiva.
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah said to רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, this is taken
from זבחים, Zevachim, I'm sorry from מנחות Menachot and זבחים Zevachim both,
אפילו אתה מרבה בשמן בשמן כל היום, afilu atta marbeh ba-shemen ba-shemen
kol ha-yom, you can quote me בשמן בשמן ba-shemen ba-shemen the entire
day, איני שומע לך, eini shome'a lach, I refuse to listen to
you. What does this mean? It means that the question is that
how much oil was the discussion was how much oil do you
bring with the loaves of bread and מצה matzah that you bring
with a תודה. todah. תודה todah is a קרבן korban for thanksgiving,
you bring loaves of bread with it. The תורה Torah says you
bring oil, it says בשמן ba-shemen multiple times. How much oil do
you bring? So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you bring a half
of a לוג. log. How do I know half of a לוג?
log? Because normally the standard measure is a לוג. log. If it
says it multiple times בשמן בשמן, ba-shemen ba-shemen, you use the rabbinic
principle of אין ריבוי אחר ריבוי אלא למעט ein ribbuy achar ribbuy
ela le-ma'et that if you're so emphasizing something you're really actually undercutting
it a little bit. Okay this is an interesting lesson in life
anyway just for what
exactly. So if it says בשמן ba-shemen so many times it's really
not the full measure, it's a half measure, חצי לוג. chatzi log.
So comes back רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah and
he doesn't disagree with the law. The law you're right. But he
just said don't don't bother me with like don't you know you
can quote your derivations because one of the things רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva was known for, right, is that he would interpret even like
the little tittles above the letters. Right so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
was very good at looking at the פסוק pasuk and using ways
to derive הלכה. halakhah. But that is contrast and I've mentioned this
a couple of times there really are like two schools when it
comes to תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-be'al peh. You know there's the
school that it is very much about passing down the tradition, מסורה,
mesorah, הלכה למשה מסיני, halakhah le-Moshe mi-Sinai, we basically are conduits to
pass down what we've received. Then there's the other school which is
the sort of human creativity, engaging the text, deriving it and you
know and that that's much more of sort of our being מחדש
mechadesh and through a process with integrity relating to the text. So
that really is in one way is sort of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva here against another tradition which is much more which actually רבי
עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva רבי, rebbe, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said I never
taught anything that I didn't first hear from my rabbis, from my
teachers. Okay so רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva much more about the creative
engagement with the text rather than just the conduit and the passing
down of tradition and here you have that as well. So if
you want to learn everything from the text you gotta be pretty
creative. and you've got to have a lot of methodology and a
lot of learning from every tittle if you want to get all
of this out of the text. But רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaryah pushes back and he says, don't bother me with
all your בשם's beshem and בשם's beshem and your attempts to learn
it from the text. This is tradition. This is passed down. Okay,
and that's what he says back. אפילו אתה מרבה בשם בשם כל
היום, Afilu ata marbe beshem beshem kol hayom, you could spend the
whole day telling me בשם בשם, beshem beshem, איני שומע לך, eini
shomeia lecha, I refuse to listen to you. אלא, Ella, here's the
story. חצי לוג שמן לתודה, Chatzi log shemen letoda, the half לוג
log שמן shemen that you use for תודה, toda, רביעית יין לנזיר,
revi'it yayin lenazir, and the fact that for a נזיר nazir there
is a רביעית revi'it of a לוג log like three and a
half ounces of wine is what a נזיר nazir is prohibited
against, ואחד עשר יום שבין נידה לנידה, ve'achad asar yom shebein nida
lenida, and the eleven days between one נידה nida period and the
next. A woman gets her period, seven days she's a נידה, nida,
this is what we've all been talking about. For the next eleven
days, eight to eighteen she won't be a נידה nida if she
bleeds then she'll be a זבה. zava. Starting on day nineteen, then
the נידה nida period begins again if she bleeds she's a נידה.
nida. So there's eleven days between נידה nida and נידה nida period.
All of those הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha lemoshe misinai. Those are הלכות
halachot from משה Moshe to סיני, Sinai, those are passed down traditions,
don't bother me with your derivations. Okay, so that's very fascinating and
it got us into our conversation because it mentioned the eleven days.
So now we've got on this we are going to have the
debate of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש. Rabbi Yochanan and Resh Lakish. מאי
הלכה? Mai halacha?
What is the הלכה halacha of these eleven days? Now תוספות Tosfot
says of course it's obvious what the הלכה halacha is. The הלכה
halacha is is that they is that like we've been saying that
for eleven days if you bleed you'll be a זבה, zava, not
a נידה. nida. But the somehow רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan
and Resh Lakish although that's clearly the point of the statement are
using this as a hook to have their discussion of the status
of the last days of that cycle, of day eleven and day
ten. So the meaning is clear and there's an eleven day gap
and you could be a זבה. zava. But on this they have
their discussion. רבי יוחנן אמר הלכה אחד עשר. Rabbi Yochanan amar halacha
achad asar. The day of eleven only has one special הלכה halacha
attached to it. What's the special הלכה halacha attached to day eleven?
That if you bleed on that day biblically you do not need
to observe the following day. ריש לקיש אמר הלכות אחד עשר. Resh
Lakish amar halachot achad asar. No, actually day eleven has two special
הלכות halachot that apply to it. What does this mean? רבי יוחנן
אמר הלכה אחד עשר, Rabbi Yochanan amar halacha achad asar, only one
special הלכה. halacha. אחד עשר הוא דלא בעי שימור. Achad asar hu
delo ba'ei shimur. Here's the special הלכה halacha of day eleven, you
don't need to observe the following day because then you're in the
נידה nida period. הא לאחריני הוי שימור, Ha leachrini havei shimur, but
if you bled on day ten, day eleven is just like any
other day in the period. Any other day in the period you
can be the day that you're observing for having bled the prior
day. So day eleven also has that הלכה. halacha. If you bled
the prior day, day ten, then day eleven can serve to be
the observed day of non-bleeding for having bled on the prior day.
So in that way day eleven is standard, it can work for
the previous day, but if you bleed on eleven you don't need
to observe the following day. So it's only one special הלכה. halacha.
ריש לקיש אמר הלכות
אחד עשר. Resh Lakish amar halachot achad asar. No, there are two
הלכות halachot that apply to day eleven. לא אחד עשר בעי שימור.
Lo achad asar ba'ei shimur. Number one, if you bleed on day
eleven you do not have to observe the following day because the
following day is your
נידה nida period. ולא שימור לאחריני הוי. Velo shimur leachrini havei. If
you bled on the prior day ten you don't need eleven to
function as the observed day because as we said it won't build
up to three days of bleeding into a זבה גדולה. zava gedola.
So eleven is special in two ways. We could really say eleven
is special and ten is special but here he's framing it as
eleven is special in two ways. If you bleed on eleven you
don't have to worry about day twelve and if you bled on
day ten you don't need to observe day eleven. Okay, so that's
the two ways. Same debate but set in the context of the
phrase הלכה למשה מסיני halacha lemoshe misinai and playing on the word
הלכה. halacha. Okay, now that we're done with that interesting debate of
רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan and Resh Lakish which we don't
resolve, we now go on and at the end of it discuss,
it's interesting again the organization, that this discussion might have been nice
to have way at the beginning of the מסכת. masechet. How do
we know this basic, all these ideas we've been talking about? That
there's an eleven day gap period that a woman could be a
זבה קטנה zava ketana if she bleeds one or two days that's
not in the תורה, Torah, the תורה Torah speaks about her being
a זבה גדולה, zava gedola, it does not speak about her being
a זבה קטנה. zava ketana. Where do we know all of these
from? And now we've been introduced to רבי אלעזר בן עזריה's Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaryah statement that it's all הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha lemoshe
misinai. It's all tradition. And now we're going to contrast that at
the end with derivations of where we learn it from the פסוקים,
pesukim, more the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva type of approach. So let's
take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this. גמרא Gemara תמהי:
t'mhei: הני הלכות נינהו? hani halachot ninhu? What? These are just הלכות?
halachot? הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha lemoshe misinai? These laws of the eleven
days? הני קראי נינהו! hani kraya ninhu! These are פסוקים pesukim that
we learn out the eleven days again like a more רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva approach to this. Where do we learn it from פסוקים
pesukim this eleven day? דתניא: Detanya: we taught in the ברייתא. Baraita.
יכול הרואה ג' ימים בתחלת נידה רצופים תהא זבה... Yachol haro'ah gimel
yamim betichlat nida retzufim tehei zava... Now the תורה Torah says, we
have a חומש Chumash here. When the תורה Torah discusses the difference
between נידה nida and זבה, zava, here's what it
says. It says, ואשה כי תהיה זבה... ve'isha ki tihiyeh zava... now
that's the הוה אמינא, havamina, נידה, nida, but actually there means flow.
In the תורה Torah נידה nida and זבה zava are... describe the
person, they describe the experience. If a woman has a flow, דם
יהיה זובה בבשרה, dam yihyeh zovah bivsarah, blood flows in her flesh,
שבעת ימים תהיה בנדתה, shiv'at yamim tihyeh veniddatah, seven days she shall
be in her נדה Niddah status, וכל הנגע בה יטמא עד הערב.
vechol hanogea bah yitma ad ha'arev. So that talks normal case she
has a flow, she's the status of a נדה. Niddah. The next
פרשה parsha says, the next section says, אשה כי יזוב זוב דמה
ימים רבים, ishah ki yazuv zov damah yamim rabbim, if the blood
flows for many days, בלא עת נדתה, belo et niddatah, not at
her regular time of נדה, Niddah, או כי תזוב על נדתה, o
ki tazuv al niddatah, or if it flows
on her נדה, Niddah, sort of more maybe a little distant from
her נדה Niddah period, presumably her normal menstrual period, then she's a
זבה. Zavah. So it says two things. It says בלא עת נדתה,
belo et niddatah, not at her normal time, but it starts by
saying ימים רבים, yamim rabbim, many days. So the first move of
the גמרא Gemara is maybe the difference between a נדה Niddah and
a זבה Zavah is if you bled one day or many days.
Maybe as soon as you bleed many days, even normal menstruation, you're
a זבה. Zavah. Okay maybe that is the difference because that's how
the תורה Torah begins, כי תזוב זוב דמה ימים רבים. ki tazuv
zov damah yamim rabbim.
And you translated או כי תזוב על נדתה o ki tazuv al
niddatah as what?
Separate from. That's how the גמרא Gemara interprets it.
Why couldn't you interpret it as like an unusually might be
right even when you're a נדה? Niddah? Okay well that's more or
less what the גמרא Gemara asks. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: יכול הרואה ג' ימים בתחילת נדה רצופים תהא זבה, yachol haroah
gimel yamim betichilat niddah retzufin tehe zavah, maybe if you just bleed
for three days straight even during your normal menstrual period you're a
זבה Zavah and because it's ימים רבים. yamim rabbim. ומה אני מקיים
אשה כי תהיה זבה דם יהיה זובה, umah ani mekayen ishah ki
tihyeh zavah dam yihye zovah, what do I do with the first
פרשה parsha which says she's a נדה Niddah not a זבה? Zavah?
דרואה יום אחד. deroah yom echad. If a woman has a very
unusual cycle, one day bleeding, she's a נדה, Niddah, but three days
bleeding even during her menstrual period maybe she'll be a זבה. Zavah.
תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, so therefore, no, don't overemphasize the ימים רבים,
yamim rabbim, look at the next phrase, next phrase, top of עג
עמוד א, Ayin Gimmel Amud Aleph, בלא עת נדתה, belo et niddatah,
not at the time of her נדה. Niddah. The point is not
that she's many days, many days is a piece of it, but
the key difference is that it's not during her menstrual period. It's
not during the time she would normally get her menstruation. This is
the idea that the difference between נדה Niddah and זבה Zavah is
the time of the month which she's bleeding. סמוך לנדתה, samuch leniddatah,
now that tells me it's not the נדה Niddah period, but it's
juxtaposed to it. Now once it makes this move, it doesn't say
this, but it assumes that when it says נדה Niddah period, the
way we define that period, the עת נדתה, et niddatah, is the
period of טומאה. tumah. So a woman bleeds, she's a נדה, Niddah,
it's her menstrual period, how long is she טמאה temeah for? Seven
days. So we are emphasizing not during her נדה Niddah period, it
means not during any of those seven days. Those seven days are
the טומאה tumah for נדה, Niddah, that's her נדה Niddah period, and
there if she bleeds after that starting on day eight, then she
can become a זבה. Zavah. That's its first move of בלא עת
נדתה belo et niddatah starting after the seven days from the onset
of bleeding.
But it also could have said the seven days she actually bled.
I understand if it was five
days and it's not that, but we still need to.
I understand right.
Okay, that's implicit. Yeah but that's implicit. Now סמוך לנדתה, samuch leniddatah,
so means the first move I would say fine, juxtaposed. If she
bleeds on day eight. Okay now we're also assuming it says כי
תזוב זוב דמה ימים רבים, ki tazuv zov damah yamim rabbim, ימים
yamim is plural and רבים rabbim goes even one further that ימים
רבים yamim rabbim means three days. That's also implicit. So now we've
said okay, bleeding after the נדה Niddah period, starting on day eight,
ימים רבים yamim rabbim means if a woman bleeds day eight, nine,
and ten. Now the question is going to be how do we
know an eleven day period? All we know now is day eight,
nine, and ten.
But you could have said רבים rabbim is two, so ימים yamim
is two
and רבים rabbim is two, making it four. We don't. סמוך לנדתה,
samuch leniddatah, juxtaposed. So days eight, nine, and ten. ואין לי אלא
סמוך לנדתה, ve'ein li ela samuch leniddatah, I only know immediately
juxtaposed, כי היכי דלהוי זבה. ki heichi delehavi zavah. מופלג לנדתה יום
אחד מנין, moflag leniddatah yom echad minayin, how about if I started
on day nine, not totally juxtaposed, one day separate? תלמוד לומר, talmud
lomar, או כי תזוב על נדתה o ki tazuv al niddatah is
the next phase. Or if she bleeds on her נדה Niddah which
is a funny phrase as Michael said you could have meant something
the exact opposite, but the גמרא Gemara understands it means a little
bit separate from. So בלא עת belo et means immediately after and
על נדה al niddah means a little separated from. So now it
understands that the emphasis is the time she's bleeding, yes you require
three days, but the time after the נדה Niddah period starting on
day eight, or a little more removed starting on day nine. So
now we have eight, nine, and ten can make her a זבה
Zavah or nine, ten, and eleven. Okay ואין לי אלא יום אחד
מנין לרבות מופלג שנים שלושה ארבעה חמישה שישה שבעה שמונה תשעה עשרה
מנין, ve'ein li ela yom echad minayin lerabbot moflag shnayim sheloshah arba'ah
chamishah shishah shiv'ah shmonah tish'ah asarah minayin, how do I know that
it's an eleven day period, right? We talked about starting on day
one of the eleven day period or day two of the eleven
day period. How do you know it's an eleven day period? Any
three days up to eleven days removed makes her a
זבה. Zavah. אמרת מה מצינו ברביעי שראוי לספירה וראוי לזיבה, amarta mah
matzinu berevi'i sheraui lesfirah veraui lezivah, the same way what's the story
about day four? Okay day four meaning if you take a look,
right, I should have had markers, but let's use this as an
example. This is her seven days and bleeding, this גמרא, Gemara, okay.
This חומש Chumash here is days one, two, and three afterwards, right?
Okay, so we said those three can make her, can make her
a זבה. Zavah. Then this גמרא Gemara here are days two, three,
and four afterwards, okay. Those can also make her a זבה, Zavah,
right? Yes. We got after the end of her נדה, Niddah, you
have one day and then days two, three, and four if she
bleeds on that, that can make her a זבה. Zavah. We learned
that from על נדתה. Al Niddatah. It doesn't have to be immediately
juxtaposed to it, it can be moved. Now day four here, what's
the character of day four? Day four, okay, is it a day
which the גמרא Gemara says hold on is it counts this is
a day that if you saw on one, two, and three, the
next seven days till ten, you would be your clean days as
a זבה. Zavah. Okay, so days four through whatever through I can't
do the math now through ten anyway, the next seven days, four
through ten, right, yeah, four through ten are your זבה Zavah period.
So day four is a period that could count as a one
of the clean
days, okay, of this, right? One of the clean days of this,
that could be day four. So the inference is something that could
count as a clean day can also be a day that if
you bleed on it can make you a זבה. Zavah. That's how
we're going to get to eleven. You understand? Day four if you
bled one, two, three could be the first of your clean days
and based on two, three, and four, it could make you a
זבה Zavah if you bleed on it. So any day that could
be one of your clean days can make you a זבה. Zavah.
So days four through ten because they can be clean days for
if you bled on one, two, three, any bleeding on four through
ten can also make you a זבה. Zavah. But remember we also
included two, three, and four. So that means bleed and if you
had blood on two, three, and four, what would make what are
your clean days? Five through eleven. So therefore any bleeding on four
through ten or five through eleven because they can be the clean
days for these two, which we say are in the פסוקים, Pesukim,
they can also be the days that would make you a זבה
Zavah if you bled on. That's how we get the eleven days.
Okay? It's easier to say it's הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai.
So דאמר D'amar so let me read it. So how do you
know to get all the way up to ten? מנין? Minayin? אמרת
Amarta מה מצינו ברביעי Ma matzinu b'revi'i שראוי לספירה? Shera'uy l'sfira? By
day four, assuming you bled on one, two, and three, day four
is a day that can be one of your clean days, of
the clean seven days. And therefore ראוי לזיבה, Ra'uy l'ziva, the assumption
is because it can serve as one of the clean seven days,
it can be a day that if you bleed on it makes
you a זבה. Zavah. That's true about day four, day four we
know. אף אני אביא העשירי Af ani avi ha'asiri I'll go all
the way from four through ten, that I will say about four
through ten שראוי לספירה, Shera'uy l'sfira, those are days that can count
as the seven clean days if you bled on one, two, and
three. So since they can count as the clean days for having
bled on one, two, and three, ראוי לזיבה, Ra'uy l'ziva, then if
you bleed on them they can make you into a זבה. Zavah.
That gets you up
to ten. ומנין לרבות אחד עשר? Uminayin l'rabot achad asar? How about
eleven? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar בלא עת נדתה. B'lo et niddatah. It
says because right we had two scenarios in the פסוקים, Pesukim, the
one-two-three scenario and the two-three-four scenario. In the two-three-four scenario, what are
the days that are your clean days? Five through eleven. So five
through eleven can be your clean days, it would also be true
that if you bleed on those days it can make you into
a זבה. Zavah. So that's how we get eleven days of that
זבה Zavah period. Now יכול שאני מרבה שנים עשר? Yachol sh'ani marbe
shneim asar? Maybe I'll go let's keep on going, let's say day
twelve can make you into a זבה Zavah period. אמרת לא. Amarta
lo. No. ומה ראית לרבות אחד עשר ולהוציא שנים עשר? Uma ra'ita
l'rabot achad asar ulehotzi shneim asar? Where do you come off saying
eleven yes and not twelve? ומה ראית לרבות אחד עשר ולהוציא שנים
עשר? Uma ra'ita l'rabot achad asar ulehotzi shneim asar? מרבה אני אחד
עשר Marbe ani achad asar שראוי לספירת או כי תזוב. Shera'uy l'sfirat
o ki tazov. So what we said, אחד עשר Achad asar gets
you can be part of the seven clean days of the בלא
עת נדתה, B'lo et niddatah, I mean על קצה זיב על נדתה.
Al kitzei ziv al niddatah. From the או כי תזוב O ki
tazov learned bleeding say two, three, and four. So if you bled
say two, three, and four, from day five through eleven can be
the seven clean days for having bled two, three, and four. So
I'll include אחד עשר Achad asar which counts as one of the
seven clean days for the או כי תזוב, O ki tazov, the
bleeding of two, three, and four, ומוציא אני שנים עשר Umotzi ani
shneim asar and I'll exclude twelve, שאין ראוי לספירת או כי תזוב,
She'ein ra'uy l'sfirat o ki tazov, that is not one of the
seven clean days. The תורה Torah describes two scenarios: bleeding day one,
two, and three after the seven days of נדה, Niddah, or two,
three, and four. It doesn't describe other scenarios. But what I'm going
to say is the clean days of one, two, and three and
two, three, and four can also count as זבה Zavah days if
you bleed based on the model of day four, but nothing more.
So that gets you days one through eleven. One minute. Okay, well
let's stop here then.
So my question is, first of all, there's a lot of you
know fancy footwork and a bit complicated, as you mentioned, הילכתא
אמרת בשפירא ושפירא כל היום, Hilchta amrat b'shafira v'shafira kol hayom, right?
Well
first of all, I guess we're going to have to answer the
question, right? Now they're saying it's still a קשיא. Kashya. Yeah, right.
But so what's
so for
something to be classified הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, meaning they
basically have like almost no basis in the תורה? Torah? Because this
is a very kind of slim basis.
Right, basically הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai means there's no claim
of any basis in the תורה, Torah, it's just a claim of
tradition. But I'll talk a little bit more about הלכה למשה מסיני.
Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai. So let's finish this discussion first.
I mean, yeah,
so it's a debate, some things are debated whether they're really based
on a פסוק Pasuk or they're just based on tradition. So let
me... So let me finish this discussion, then I'll go back. Okay,
so now we're continuing. So now we got our 11 days. ואין
לי אלא שלשה ימים. ve'ein li ella shlosha yamim. Now, the Torah
only discusses a זבה zava who bleeds ימים רבים, yamim rabim, which
we say means three, and then it says seven clean days. It
does not discuss any smaller stint of a זבה, zava, one day
or two days, that that's a problem, that you need one clean
day. None of that is discussed in the Torah. ואין לי אלא
שלשה ימים. ve'ein li ella shlosha yamim. שני ימים מנין? shnei yamim
minayin? How do I know if a woman only bleeds two days
that that's also a type of a זבה? zava? תלמוד לומר ימי.
talmud lomar yemei, So it says יום—sorry, yom ימי.
yemei. I skipped a word. ימי. yemei. So it says ימי. yemei.
ימי yemei. which is two. What's the פסוק? pasuk? ימים רבים או
כל ימי זוב טומאתה. yamim rabim o kol yemei zov tumata. All
the days, so ימי yemei is not ימים, yamim, it's only in
the simple plural, therefore it means two, it doesn't mean three. Right,
ימים רבים yamim rabim is the doubled plural, so it means three,
but ימי yemei means two. Okay. I know, I know. Anyway, יום
אחד. yom echad. So יום אחד מנין? yom echad minayin, Fine, that
gives you a two-day version. Where do you get a one-day version?
תלמוד לומר כל ימי. talmud lomar kol yemei, So all of the
days. Now, you might think that that's more inclusive, but all could
also mean like any of the days is how it's reading it.
So it's reading the ימי כל ימי yemei kol yemei to tell
you there's a concept of a זבה zava of being only two
days or one day, not the three-day explicit case in the Torah.
Okay. טמאה. tmeiah. So if she bleeds even one day or two
days she is טמאה. tmeiah. ללמד שמטמא את בועלה כנדה. lelamed shemetamei
et boala kenidah. For so it says טמאה היא, tmeiah hi, she
is טמאה, tmeiah, this woman who is a זבה zava whether it's
a three-day זבה, zava, a two-day זבה, zava, a one-day זבה, zava,
she is טמאה. tmeiah. So what does that come to include? It
comes to include other aspects of the טומאה tumah of זבה zava
that are not mentioned explicitly in the Torah. The Torah does mention
things she sits on are טמא. tamei. It does not mention the
status of the man she has sex with, which it did mention
by a נדה. niddah. So here we're saying this general statement that
she is טמאה, tmeiah, זבה zava again whether קטנה ktana or גדולה,
gdola, whether two-day or three-day זבה, zava, if her husband has, a
man has sex with her that man becomes equal טמא tamei as
her. Not just for touching her which would be a ראשון, rishon,
but just as טמא tamei as she is, he would be an
אב. av. Now I do want to point out that the גמרא
Gemara is also not saying another very important thing not mentioned by
נדה niddah but assumed to be true by זבה zava as well,
which is also about sex, but much more relevant for us, which
is the prohibition to have sex. The biblical prohibition to have sex,
which it says is prohibited by כרת, karet, is only said by
a נדה. niddah. It's not said by a זבה, zava, it's not
said by a יולדת, yoledet, it's not said by anybody else who
has—but the גמרא Gemara assumes since the טומאה tumah is the same,
and the טומאה tumah is compared, the prohibition of sex is also
the same. So it's interesting here that the other thing it has
to include is the טומאה tumah that transfers via sex, because those
are things that are not mentioned in the Torah about a זבה.
zava. דאורייתא? de'oraita? דאורייתא. de'oraita. Okay. How's it transfer? הטומאה? hatumah? How
does any טומאה tumah transfer? Because the Torah says it does. I
mean, you know, the mechanics of טומאה tumah are just based on
what the Torah says happens. It says it transfers different if you're
touching a metal vessel or if you're touching a pottery vessel, different—you
know, so here the Torah says one way טומאה tumah transfers is
a man having sex with a woman who's a נדה. niddah. But
if he's זב, zav, he doesn't transfer. Right, as we mentioned yesterday.
It's not—it's not a generic statement that an act of sex transfers
טומאה. tumah. It's a very specific—and if a man has sex with
a woman who's a מצורע, metzora, it doesn't transfer. It's a very
specific... She's the transferor. Right, but not—but in the cases of נדה
niddah and זבה, zava, right, but I just want to point out
that there are cases even the woman doesn't transfer to the man,
like if she's a מצורע metzora and he has sex with her,
it wouldn't transfer. But in the cases of נדה niddah and זבה,
zava, right, it's only in one direction transfer. Right, exactly. Right. Correct.
But the sex is not transferable. Well, it is in this case.
I mean, what do you mean?
The טומאה tumah is transferable. So the same way—look, if a woman
sits, if a woman sits on a seat, that seat is an
אב הטומאה. av hatumah. If a woman's נדה niddah or זבה zava
sits on a seat, that seat is just as טמא tamei as
she is. If a man זב zav sits on a seat, that
seat is just as
טמא tamei as he is.
If a man or woman, זב zav or זבה zava or whatever,
touches a piece of fruit or vessel, it's one degree removed. Okay?
So sometimes a זב zav and a זבה zava or נדה niddah
sits to make something equal to them as they sit on a
seat.
Sometimes, most of the times, it
makes it one degree removed. The normal transfer makes it one degree
less, that's if you touch it. So what the Torah is saying
is if a man has sex with a woman who's a נדה
niddah and now we're extending it to זבה, zava, it's like the
seat that a נדה niddah sits on, which is that it has
equal טומאה tumah as she does.
The same way if he sits on a seat it's equal, or
if a man זב zav sits on a seat it's equal to
him, it's not lower, so by the case of the—of a man
having sex with the—of the woman being a נדה niddah and the
man having sex with her, his status is equal to her, is
an אב. av. I understand, I understand. I'm not—I'm not explaining—right, I
don't—right, I'm not explaining, I'm not explaining the asymmetry. I'm just pointing
out—trying to get us to understand the difference of saying equal level
of טומאה, tumah, it doesn't mean that you're now—the man is now
a נדה. niddah. Okay? The same way you don't say that the
cushion is now a נדה. niddah. It just means that the level
of טומאה tumah is the first level of טומאה, tumah, it's not
a derived—it's not a derived level of טומאה. tumah. But what should
be the logic? Yeah, so we discussed that yesterday. I mean, I
don't have—I don't have anything new since yesterday. Okay? All right, so
that's how we know it applies to a זבה zavah as well,
but in addition to the laws of טומאה tumah that are not
so relevant to us as I said, is the important point that's
not explicit here, that the prohibition of sex is also applied in
the case of a זבה. zavah. Now the תורה Torah goes on
and it says תמאה היא, tme'ah hi, it says כימי נדתה תהיה,
kimei niddatah tihyeh, like the days of her נידה, niddah, the תורה
Torah is very clear to explicitly link them. תמאה היא, tme'ah hi,
היא hi is תמאה. tme'ah. So one thing we get is that
her husband or the man who has sex with her becomes טמא.
tamei. And then it says, one minute, כנדתה תהיה היא, keniddatah tihyeh
hi, היא, hi, she is, היא ותטמא בועלה, hi uttema bo'alah, here
you go Rivka, ואין הזב מטמא מה שהוא בועל. ve'ein hazav mettame
mah shehu bo'el. Now they, right, yeah, sure, they are with this
אסמכתא. asmachta. She, היא, hi, she, it makes the man, the person
she has sex with טמא, tamei, but הוא hu does not make
the woman he has sex with if he's a זב zav טמא.
tamei. Now I've got to tell you in addition to the asymmetry,
I, what I find a little disturbing here is the מה שהוא
בועל, mah shehu bo'el, which is sort of very objectifying. It's not
מי שהוא בועל, mi shehu bo'el, מה שהוא בועל, mah shehu bo'el,
right? So I think that to me, I think that has something
to do with the asymmetry, that she is like a טמא tamei
object, so he handles her, it transfers to him, whereas if he
is, what? whereas if he is טמא. tamei. All right, anyway, I
think, I think the question, I think the question of who is
the object, who, I think the question of who is the object,
who is the subject, has something to do with this asymmetry. Anyway,
that's what we learn out from היא. hi. Now, תלמוד לומר, talmud
lomar we're not going to give this one up so easily, Rivka,
we're going to try to push it. Maybe I should say argue
by a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה היא שאינה מטמאה בראיות כבימים,
umah hi she'eina mettame'ah bi'reiyot kiyyamim, when a woman is a נידה,
niddah, she becomes a נידה, niddah, it's not as easy for her
to be a זבה zavah in a certain way as it is
for a man to be a זב. zav. Why? Because if she
bleeds three times, that doesn't make her, I mean, not נידה, niddah,
excuse me, זבה. zavah. If she bleeds three times, it doesn't make
her a זבה. zavah. She has to bleed in three consecutive days.
If it's not over three consecutive days, if it's three times on
one day or three times over five days, it doesn't count. It's
only three consecutive days. She is not מטמא mettame by seeing as
she is by days, meaning it requires days to be a component,
and she as a זבה zavah מטמאה בועלה, mettame'ah bo'alah, makes the
man she has sex with טמא. tamei. הוא, hu, when a man
is a זב, zav, שמטמא בראיות כבימים, shemettame bi'reiyot kiyyamim, for him
he becomes a זב zav easier. If he has his flow three
times on the same day, he's a זב. zav. Anywhere between three
times on the same day to within three consecutive days. But it
doesn't, I'm sorry, twice. Thank you, three is for a קרבן. korban.
Twice. Yeah, could have said that too. But anyway, even the full
level, the point is is that for him, he does not need
it to be on separate days. Even if it's twice or three
times on the same day, so he could become a זב zav
easier in that sense. So if that's true, if the טומאה tumah
is in a certain sense easier, אינו דין שמטמא מה שהוא בועל,
eino din shemettame mah shehu bo'el, isn't it, doesn't it, isn't it
logical that he should make טמא tamei again what, not who, what
he is having sex with? We'll say who. Okay, תלמוד לומר היא.
talmud lomar hi. So that's why it says היא, hi, she, היא
מטמאה בועלה, hi mettame'ah bo'alah, only she makes the man she has
sex with טמא, tamei, ואין הזב, ve'ein hazav, but if a man
is a זב, zav, הוא אינו מטמא מה שהוא בועל, hu eino
mettame mah shehu bo'el, the woman that he has sex with. So
that's what we learn out emphasizing the asymmetry, but again, I think
that the use of מה mah as opposed to מי mi is
significant. ומנין, u'minayin, what? I, you can't, that is like staring you
in the face. ומנין שהוא עושה משכב ומושב? u'minayin shehu oseh mishkav
u'moshav? Now, how do you know שהיא עושה, shehi oseh, right? You
say שהיא shehi here somewhere, right? Yeah, ומנין שיש לה היא. u'minayin
sheyesh lah hi. How do you know that this woman who is,
not this woman, the תורה Torah is, the גמרא Gemara is, the
תורה Torah is explicit that a classic זבה zavah makes משכב ומושב.
mishkav u'moshav. The next פסוק pasuk is כל המשכב אשר תשכב עליו
כל ימי זובה כמשכב נדתה יהיה לה וכל הכלי אשר תשב עליו
טמא יהיה כטמאת נדתה. kol hammishkav asher tishkav alav kol yemei zovah
kemishkav niddatah yihyeh lah vechol hakkeli asher teshev alav tamei yihyeh ketum'at
niddatah. But now we're including, we're going back to the זבה קטנה,
zavah ketannah, a woman who bled only one or two days, which
we got from a hint in the פסוק. pasuk. How do you
know her status is equal? That even things she sits on are
an אב הטומאה, av hattumah, the highest level of טומאה? tumah? So
how do you know that? תלמוד לומר כמשכב נדתה. talmud lomar kemishkav
niddatah. I'm sorry, no, I'm sorry, I jumped ahead. So first it
says how do you know it's true by a normal זבה? zavah?
So okay, that's explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. It says כמשכב נדתה,
kemishkav niddatah, that if she sits on it she makes it טמא
tamei like if she was a נידה. niddah. ואין לי אלא שלושה
ימים, ve'ein li ella sheloshah yamim, I only know in the explicit
case in the תורה Torah three days, there it's quite explicit. שני
ימים מנין, shenei yamim minayin, how do I know even for a
two-day זבה zavah this is true? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar ימי, yemei
because that same פסוק, pasuk, no, in this, this פסוק pasuk as
well by the משכב, mishkav, it repeats כל ימי זובה. kol yemei
zovah. So it said כל ימי kol yemei. in the previous פסוק
pasuk to say she was טמאה, tme'ah, and now it says כל
ימי kol yemei to say that she makes a משכב. mishkav. So
ימי yemei means two days. Even a two-day זבה. zavah. יום אחד
yom echad מנין, minayin? how about a one-day זבה? zavah? תלמוד לומר
talmud lomar, כל ימי, kol yemei which we're reading to mean any
of the days. Okay, so basically we got, what did we get
from the פסוק? pasuk? A lot of things that are not explicit.
We got the eleven-day gap, we got the fact that... that that
there's a concept of a זבה zavah. קטנה *zava ketana* of a
one or two-day זבה zavah. *zava*, which is not explicit anywhere in
the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*, and we got the idea that she also
makes the man she's having sex with טמא tamei *tamei*, but that's
true by her and it's not by a זב *zav*, and what's
not explicitly stated here but as it's critical for us nowadays is
that the prohibition of sex applies equally to a זבה *zava* and
a נדה niddah *niddah*. That's not even being said, but it's implicit.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says one last point about this.
Okay, ומניין שסופרת אחד לאחד *Uminayin shesoferet echad le'echad*? How do you
know that if a woman bleeds only one day, she has to
keep a clean day, observe a clean day following? That's not in
the תורה Torah *Torah* either, right? We learned out that כי היא
*ki hi* that that one or two days also counts. Maybe it
should be a seven-day טומאה *tumah*? How do you know, a, that
it's not seven and, b, that maybe you need nothing, you know,
how do you know that you need one and that one suffices?
As if you count even if you're bleeding just two. We'll get
to that. We'll get to that. We'll get to that. תלמוד Talmud.
לומר *Talmud lomar* יהיה לה *yihyeh lah*. It should be for her,
which somehow we're רש"י *Rashi* says, let me just check the רש"י
*Rashi*, right. So רש"י *Rashi* says it means she should have something.
She has to observe something for this. It sort of takes for
granted she doesn't need seven days. Seven days is only for what's
explicit in the תורה Torah, *Torah*, bleeding three days. Okay? So when
we then say כל ימי *kol yemei*, there's another case of one
or two, how do maybe she need nothing? No, יהיה לה *yihyeh
lah*. Does the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* say כל משכב אשר תשכב עליו
כל ימי זובה כמשכב נדתה יהיה לה *kol mishkav asher tishkav alav
kol yemei zovah kemishkav niddatah yihyeh lah*? Right, but it goes on
ימי זובה *yemei zovah*, כל ימי *kol yemei*. Right. Anyway, somehow it's
learning it from the יהיה לה *yihyeh lah* which is connected to
the words כל ימי *kol yemei*. From כל ימי *kol yemei* we
get one or two days bleeding. We're assuming not seven clean days.
How do you know any clean days? יהיה לה *yihyeh lah* means
you need something for it. You need one clean day to be
observed for it. Okay, where were we? ומניין שסופרת אחד לאחד יהיה
לה *Uminayin shesoferet echad le'echad yihyeh lah*. יכול תספור שבעה לשניים *Yachol
tispor shiv'ah lishnayim*? Okay, maybe for two days though she should have
to do all seven? ודינו *Vedino*, it makes sense, because as a,
they pointed out there, זב *zav* for two days has to keep
seven. ומה הוא *Umah hu* by a זב *zav*? שתי ראיות *Shtei
re'iyot*, thank you, שאין סופר אחד לאחד *she'ein sofer echad le'echad*. If
a זב *zav* has one flow, one one one experience of flow,
he does not have to keep a clean day. Nevertheless, סופר שבעה
לשניים *sofer shiv'ah lishnayim*. If he has two flows, he needs seven
clean days. היא *Hi*, she, שסופרת אחד לאחד *shesoferet echad le'echad*, she
that even for one day needs to observe a following clean day,
אינו דין שתספור שבעה לשניים *eino din shetispor shiv'ah lishnayim*? Maybe for
two days of flow, she should need seven like a זב *zav*?
So תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar* יהיה לה *yihyeh lah*. No, the יהיה
לה *yihyeh lah* is going on the כל ימי *kol yemei*. כל
ימי *kol yemei* is one or two days. So for כל ימי
*kol yemei*, whether it's one day or two days, all you get
is יהיה לה *yihyeh lah*, just one observance. אינה סופרת אלא יום
אחד *Eina soferet ela yom echad*. יהיה לה *Yihyeh lah*, the same,
you know, one thing is for her just one day, end of
story. Anyway, יהיה לה *yihyeh lah* the same number of days that
she was טמאה *tameiah*? Yeah, so that's the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, yeah,
that you would have wanted to ask. Maybe it should be one
day for one and two days for two? Yeah, that it asks
elsewhere, it doesn't ask here. But again, somehow it's the same יהיה
לה *yihyeh lah* that applies equally for both. So now you saw
actually it's one day of of yeah. Yeah, that's what we've been
assuming the whole time, yes. So whether a woman bleeds one or
two days, if she's still a זבה קטנה *zava ketana*, it's only
one clean day, it's not seven clean days. Okay, and it's not
two for two either. Okay, so all of this we got from
the פסוקים pesukim, *pesukim*. Some of it was pretty straightforward. השוואת טומאה
לנדה *Hashva'at tumah leniddah*, משכב ומושב *mishkav umoshav*, maybe the בועל *bo'el*
case as well, the man she has sex with, because the תורה
Torah, *Torah* explicitly links this. But a lot of it was not
nearly so clear. Okay, there's an eleven-day period that you could be
a זבה *zava*. That was very, you know, ingenious how the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* got derived that. The idea that there's a whole category
of a זבה קטנה *zava ketana* is not at all clear in
the תורה Torah *Torah* and certainly not that then there's this idea
of one clean day. All of that was done through דרשה drasha
*derasha*, not through הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai. *halacha leMoshe miSinai*.
So now we go back. How did ר' אלעזר בן עזריה *Rebbi
Elazar ben Azaryah* say to ר' עקיבא *Rebbi Akiva*, don't drain your
hair with שמן ושמן *shemen vashemen*, you know, it's all הלכה למשה
מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai. *halacha leMoshe miSinai*, this and the eleven days
and so on? Here we see it's not הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
L’Moshe MiSinai *halacha leMoshe miSinai*. Here we see that it's derived. So
what does the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* say? אלמא קראי *Alma kra'ei*. You
see it's פסוקים *pesukim*. So ר' עקיבא *Rebbi Akiva* קראי *krai*, ר'
אלעזר בן עזריה *Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah* הלכתא היא *hilchata hi*. Yeah,
it's exactly the debate. The same way they debate where you know
the idea of the half לוג *log* of oil for a תודה
*todah*, they debate the question of the eleven days. ר' עקיבא *Rebbi
Akiva* would say you learn it from פסוקים *pesukim* and ר' אלעזר
בן עזריה *Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah* says you have it from tradition.
And this, as I said, is really not just this narrow debate.
There really is the two major schools, alive, you know, alive and
healthy even today about general attitude towards תורה שבעל פה Torah She’ba’al
Peh *Torah sheba'al peh*. How much is this? Everything was already handed
down, already figured out, basically what we're doing is just, you know,
passing and being the conduit and so on, and how much is
it effectively everything is all הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai, *halacha
leMoshe miSinai*. And how much is it, no, it's here for us
to discover, for us to figure out. And ר' עקיבא *Rebbi Akiva*
approach, even to דרשן *darshan* every little tittle and somehow get eleven
days, you know, an eleven-day period out of these פסוקים *pesukim*, which
is the ר' עקיבא *Rebbi Akiva* approach. So I'll say one or
two things about the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai, *halacha leMoshe
miSinai* related to that that Michael asked, which is... So here you
have a debate whether something is הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai,
or not. You also have it in the בשמן ובשמן. Bashemen V’Bashemen.
You also have it as Michael said by the ניסוך המים, Nisuch
Hamayim, by water. Now, the whole question of whether תורה שבעל פה
Torah She’ba’al Peh is derived or passed down was very important for
the רמב"ם Rambam in his fights with the קראים, Karaim, maybe in
general but also particularly in his fights with the קראים Karaim because
the קראים Karaim use basically, a nice thing to say are the
end of, it’s at the end of ש"ס, Shas, use all of
the debates which for us is such a wonderful part of learning
גמרא, Gemara all of the arguments and disagreements and debates as evidence
against Rabbinic Judaism. They say, how can you guys say that you
have all these traditions and that you know what the תורה Torah.
means, right, if you’re always debating? So obviously you don’t know, you
have no idea, you have no tradition, no מסורה, mesorah, so they
rejected Rabbinic Judaism. So רמב"ם’s Rambam’s response to that was was that
look, there are parts which are straight down handed tradition which we
guys have and you guys don’t, and the rest, the debates are
not because we’re debating what was originally said way back when. The
debates are because the vast majority of תורה, Torah, תורה שבעל פה
Torah She’ba’al Peh is derived, and if it’s derived by human creativity
and using certain methods and so on, naturally there will be different
types of conclusions that you can reach. It’s not one thing, one
answer that we’re disagreeing about. We’re all deriving things in different ways,
and that’s what the majority of תורה שבעל פה Torah She’ba’al Peh
is. So the disagreement does not mean we don’t know the הלכה,
halacha, these debates? No, he’s not saying that. He’s saying the הלכה
halacha was not predetermined. A tiny amount of the תורה Torah שבעל
פה was handed down. That’s הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai. That
he said is like, he said it’s almost infinitesimal, it’s tiny. The
vast majority of תורה, sorry, 99.9% was done, was not predetermined what
it means, was given to people, to the rabbis, you know, whatever,
to derive through using the methodology, through using the hermeneutic principles, and
it was open-ended what it would be and therefore that’s why you
have disagreement. It’s not because we lost the tradition, it’s because the
natural process of derivation will lead to different opinions. Now, that’s what
he says. But part of making that argument then to defend against
the קראים Karaim was that he also said, he doesn’t say defending
against the קראים, Karaim, he just says it, but historically we sort
of see that that’s what was going on. He says that the
הלכות למשה מסיני Halachot L’Moshe MiSinai which were passed down were never
debated. Those everybody agreed on. Of course, the funny thing is that
even in the הלכות למשה מסיני Halachot L’Moshe MiSinai you see that
there’s debates about whether something really was a הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha
L’Moshe MiSinai, So maybe we could nuance what the רמב"ם Rambam is
really saying to be that the הלכה halacha of the הלכה למשה
מסיני halakha lemoshe misinai was never debated. It might have been debated
whether it was a הלכה למשה מסיני, halakha lemoshe misinai but never
nobody ever debated the fact, like the הלכה halacha of 11 days
or the הלכה halacha of the חצי לוג chatzi log of נזיר
nazir or so on. Even that is not so clear. But anyway,
so that’s one thing which is important, these two schools, if you
would, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar
ben Azariah, and which is the dominant school, the רמב"ם Rambam completely
weighs in favor of the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva school because of
the importance of explaining the nature of the debates in the תלמוד.
Now, the interesting thing of course that, you know, I’ll just add
to that is, and then we’ll go into questions, is that for
some people the issue was a different problem, not the קראים Karaim
and so on. For some people like in the 19th century with
Reform, the Reform mocked the derivations in the גמרא. Gemara, You know,
they said, come on, that’s a joke. You’re going to tell me
from this כל כל ימי, kol kol yemei, blah blah blah, that
you’re going to really learn out 11 days? Those things are a
joke and therefore the whole enterprise is a joke because this derivation
really these derivations don’t make any sense. They’re not rational, they don’t
make any sense. To which one set of responses was, can you
imagine what the response would be? These aren’t really derived, really we
knew all of this from tradition. Okay, but it’s all הלכה למשה
מסיני, halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. or you know, whether הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai tradition is how we’ve always been practicing tradition, and whatever,
הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai Then the going back and linking
it to the פסוקים, that was an after-the-fact type of thing, that
was essentially an אסמכתא. asmachta. Okay, so it’s very interesting depending on
what sort of is the critique, right, where you’re sort of emphasizing
the school of it’s all tradition and passed down or it’s almost
all derived and so on. So you know, Michael is correct that
sometimes it’s not clear. Sometimes the גמרא Gemara quotes a פסוק, pasuk.
you know, and so on, and you don’t know, bottom line, are
you really telling me you’re learning it from the פסוק? pasuk, Or
are you telling me you’re just linking it but it’s really a
tradition? Maybe it’s even דרבנן d’rabbanan and you’re just quoting a פסוק.
pasuk. So sometimes there’s a lot of ambiguity, but even when things
are דאורייתא, d’oraita, are seen to be as biblical as the interpretation,
the question still is how much is that about the passed down
understanding and how much is that and then the link to the
פסוק, either we don’t even bother linking it, we call it הלכה
halakha למשה מסיני, or the link is just an after-the-fact, and how
much is it really derived, how much is it the school of
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and how much is it the school of
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה? Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah? Is there a question
in the back? No? Okay, yes. One minute, Charlie, what? I'm getting
to you in a second, Charlie. Charlie, I'm getting to you in
a second. We have a question from the back. Yes. Are the
principles הלכה halacha למשה מסיני handed down? Oh, yes, so that's also
assumed and thank you for mentioning that. It's also assumed that the
מידות שהתורה נדרשת בהן middot shehatorah nidreshet bahen are also, you know,
הלכה halacha למשה מסיני to some degree were handed down. Of course,
the problem because or else it becomes circular, right? Then how do
you know to what what are the guiding principles? So you have
to sort of get off the dime somehow, you know, so you
have to have those principles given. The problem is that even those
principles are debated, as we know. Some say כלל ופרט וכלל, klal
uperat uklal, some say ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי. ribuy umiut uribuy. So how
do you deal with that? I don't know. But the assumption is
that yes, those principles are handed down. I should also say that,
you know, it's important that, you know, this gets into the larger
question of, well, can you say the תורה means whatever you want
it to say if it's all about derivation, that there's still very
much what the גמרא Gemara says that you couldn't sit on the
סנהדרין Sanhedrin unless you could find 70 ways to say that a
שרץ sheretz was טהור. tahor. You know, to say that like something
that's obviously טמא was טהור, tahor, which means that the גמרא Gemara
acknowledges that you can come to any conclusion you want. Okay? So
the so therefore if you're smart enough and you know enough of
the rules and enough of the how to whatever you can come
to any conclusion you want. Part of of course what makes it
legitimate is the integrity of the process. And the רמב״ם Rambam did
does actually say, because he has to deal with a problem with
that the גמרא, Gemara the משנה Mishnah says, שמשרבו תלמידי בית שמאי
ובית הלל שלא שימשו את רבותיהם כל צרכן רבתה מחלוקת בישראל. shemishe-rabu
talmidei Beit Shammai v'Beit Hillel shelo shimshu et raboteihem kol tzorkhan ravta
machloket b'Yisrael. When the students of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית
הלל Beit Hillel didn't spend enough time, you know, sort of attending
to their masters, their teachers, and their studies and so on, that
led to all of this all of these debates. So it sounds
like they forgot what was said. And it sounds like it's about
breaking of the chain and you know not learn not getting the
traditions from their masters. But the רמב״ם Rambam says no, it's not
it's about not learning well enough how to do the process of
derivation. Even the process of derivation you have to learn how to
do it in a rigorous manner. So according to the רמב״ם, Rambam,
the debates are, you know, if we all sort of it's an
interesting question in the רמב״ם Rambam whether he thinks that if we
all at the highest level would we all come out, you know,
in terms of intelligence and integrity and so on, would we all
come out with the same conclusions or naturally would there be multiple
conclusions anyway? Because it is a גמרא Gemara that says that the
debates were a result of בית שמאי Beit Shammai the students of
שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel not attending enough to their studies. Yes.
So if you're going through a derivation process then what you end
up with should not really be similar to what you started out
with. And and the proof being? Right. Right. Well wait, wait. This
is the last point. I was ending by telling us that there's
no expectation that how we would end would be how we started.
Well, let's finish the very end of the גמרא Gemara because it's
going to end with a certain dialectic. Charlie, what do you want
to say before we wrap the whole thing up? I was thinking
that the לא בשמים היא lo bashamayim hi would be support for
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Oh, yes, that is true that's an excellent
point. And the לא בשמים היא lo bashamayim hi certainly is, you
know, people love that story of רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaria and the walls bending in and why לא בשמים היא
lo bashamayim hi God you stay out of this, but there are
other ways of explaining it. One way of explaining it is that
God maybe allows us to make mistakes because that's what's necessary for
there to be a central authority of law. So not that not
that what they say creates law regardless of what God sort of
says the הלכה halacha should be. That's the way I think the
simple sense of that and certainly the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva approach
and the רמב״ם Rambam approach and also רמב״ן על התורה. Ramban al
haTorah. But those that want to emphasize the idea that there's one
truth that we're discovering that it's all mostly it's all basically tradition
and so on, not that you know they read that גמרא Gemara
that God sort of says fine, I'm going to step away,
I'm going to let you make any those mistakes because
in the end you need to have a central authority that decides
things whether it's from getting it right or getting it wrong. So
that's the way that's that's that's the way the חינוך Chinuch explains
that story. Not that they created law, but that God allows those
mistakes to be made. Okay, yes. And now as the titular head
of the Divinity School. To what extent today do the halakhic authorities
why authority do they have to continue this process? Is it frozen?
So that's so right, so so that's the question. It is an
ongoing interpretive process and anybody who reads any of the responsa literature
sees that. The question is number one, which things are you know
which what is the potential range first of all our text that
we interpret is not the תורה. Our text that we interpret is
basically like the גמרא Gemara and the ראשונים. Rishonim. That that's like
a shift that happened. You know we tend to think that even
the תנאים Tannaim even the אמוראים Amoraim didn't interpret the תורה, they
only interpreted the תנאים, Tannaim, but that's not true. We do find
אמוראים Amoraim that make מדרשות midrashot like שמואל. Shmuel. One of the
central laws in הלכות נדה Hilchos Niddah that only with הרגשה hargasha
is a woman a נדה niddah does it from making a דרשה
on a פסוק. But for us post-גמרא Gemara. the text that we
interpret is not the תורה the text we interpret is the גמרא
Gemara and you know to some and the ראשונים. Rishonim. But yes
ongoing process of פסק psak is an ongoing you know interpretation of
those. But the question is how do you you know which is
always the question what defines an interpretation that is within an acceptable
range outside of an acceptable range you know that is sort of
you know keeping within you know being done with integrity and keeping
within a sense of continuity. What’s considered a break and so on?
So you know those are all I think questions that cannot be
given straight answers to but you know but those are the questions
that need to be raised. I thought there’s גמרא מנחות Gemara Menachos
where משה Moshe was watching... Right and he was sitting in the
back row. Right. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva exactly that גמרא Gemara
is a perfect thank you for bringing that up. That גמרא Gemara
is perfect bringing the two sort of concepts together. Thank you Rachel.
Where רבי Rabbi right you know the story that רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva משה Moshe is put into רבי עקיבא’s Rabbi Akiva class and
he wants to know what those little dots and tittles are for.
And anyway he gets in the front row he can’t understand what’s
going on. He gets into the he keeps on going into the
back of the class. And then finally someone says to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva he says רבי מנאיין לך? Rabbi minayin lecha? And he
says הלכה halacha למשה מסיני. And משה’s Moshe happy again. So that’s
exactly that is exactly it. So let’s with that in mind let’s
wrap up the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. אמר ליה רב שמיא לרבי אבא.
Amar lei Rav Shmaya le-bi-Abba. Rav Shmaya said to Abba אימא eima
so we can’t end without one final question about this these הלכות.
halachos. אימא ביממא תהוי זבה ובליליא תהוי נדה. Eima bi-yamama tehei zavah
u-be-laya tehei niddah. Going back to what you said is whether it’s
during the נדה niddah period seven days or the eleven days. Maybe
the difference is that it says ימים yamim days. So maybe she
bleeds at night she’s a נדה niddah she bleeds in the day
she’s a זבה. So ובליליא תהוי u-be-laya tehei אמר ליה הלכה מקרא
אל נדתה amar lei Alacha mikra al niddatah that she’s bleeding directly
opposite against her נדה niddah which means סמוך לנדתה. samuch le-niddatah. Interesting
before we said it meant a day removed but anyway juxtaposed. סמוך
לנדתה samuch le-niddatah אמתאי הויא? eimatai havaia? So when is immediately after
her נדה niddah period? Her נדה niddah period ends at nightfall of
day seven. So immediately afterwards is בליליא be-laya the night of day
eight וקרי לה זבה ve-karei la zavah and it calls her a
זבה. So I don’t know you know anyway it’s a funny question
it’s a funny answer. But now very nicely it gets back to
what I think is the early discussion. תוספות Tosfos says this last
line has nothing to do with anything it’s just to have a
nice line to end the גמרא Gemara and we could say to
end the ש"ס. shas. But I think it very much does tie
into what we’ve been discussing. Are we going to finish it now?
Yes. Let’s oh so we not read the last line? Are we
doing the are we doing the... We’ll do the קדיש Kaddish we’ll
do the formal סיום siyum later. We’re going to read the last
line. Okay. תנא דבי אליהו. Tana de-bei Eliyahu. You’ll this might be
familiar to people right you have it in the davening. They teach
in the house of Eliyahu כל השונה הלכות בכל יום מובטח לו
שהוא בן עולם הבא שנאמר הליכות עולם לו אל תקרי הליכות אלא
הלכות. kol ha-shoneh halachos be-chol yom muvtach lo she-hu ben olam ha-ba
she-ne’emar halichos olam lo al tikrei halichos ela halachos. Somebody who learns
הלכה halacha then עולם לו olam lo the world is to him
עולם הבא. olam ha-ba. So I think that this is very significant
number one because you know A a הלכה could be like י"א
יום בין נדה לנדה. yud-alef yom bein niddah le-niddah. The גמרא in
נדה or actually the גמרא in ברכות Brachos we’re actually going to
say gives that as an example of הלכה פסוקה. halacha pesuka. Okay
so the idea of הלכה פסוקה halacha pesuka like a simple you
know straightforward הלכה you know not debated. י"א יום בין נדה לנדה.
yud-alef yom bein niddah le-niddah. It also says that that רבי זירא’s
Rabbi Zeira בנות ישראל החמירו על עצמן benot Yisrael hichmiru al atzman
is an example of that. So anyway that ties into כל השונה
הלכות kol ha-shoneh halachos the eleven days before and the הלכה למשה
מסיני whether it’s הלכה למשה מסיני or not. But what I also
think it ties into is this ending of this almost dialectic of
the passing on and the creative process. Because שונה הלכות shoneh halachos
what words come from שונה? shoneh? What word? שינוי? shinei? No no
no that wasn’t what I was talking about. משנה. Mishnah. So הלכות
halachos are not גמרא. הלכות halachos are bottom line פסק. psak. Okay
so the גמרא’s ending by telling you okay this was amazing this
was all of this you know sort of discussion and debate or
whatever but you know you can’t forget bottom line הלכה you’ve got
to know bottom line הלכה so part of your day has to
include a little learning of the bottom line. But that I think
is also part of this ongoing dialectic right how much is it
straight teachings that are passed down which is a critical part of
the process and how much is it the ongoing discussion debate and
dialectic which obviously makes up what is so beautiful about our our
that’s what dialectic means. So obviously that’s what let me just end
you can say... anyway so that with that we will end so
this wonderful twelfth cycle of learning of ש"ס shas and יישר כח
yashar koach to everybody particularly those that have that have done the
entire process and look forward to celebrating with all of you on
Monday night. הדרן לך תינוקות וסליקא לך מסכת נדה. Hadran lach Tinokos
u-selichah lach maseches Niddah. Beginning ברכות Brachos tomorrow. הדרן לך תינוקות, Hadran
lach Tinokos, סליקא לך מסכת נדה. Selika lach Masechet Niddah. Beginning ברכות
Brachos tomorrow. Okay. Thank you.